<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Electric Python]]></title>
  <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-09T13:04:11+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://NigelCleland.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nigel Cleland]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction and blog content]]></title>
    <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/2013/05/09/introduction-and-blog-content/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-09T12:43:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/2013/05/09/introduction-and-blog-content</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, first a brief introduction.
My name is Nigel and I am currently a Ph.D student at the University of Auckland, New Zealand.
My current research is on market based systems for procuring security (reserve) in electricity markets.
In particular, I do a substantial amount of data analysis attempting to assess the consequences and frequency of constrained situations.
I&rsquo;m currently ~1.5 years into this.</p>

<p>This blog is intended to serve as predominately writing practice, as well as thoughts on technical and esoteric matters.
I try to use open source software as much as possible in my day to day work with Python, LaTeX and Ubuntu being the main elements.
I would like to contribute more to open source in the future, however I&rsquo;m not entirely sure on the best way to accomplish this.
Hopefully, some blog posts on semi technical matters may provide a stepping stone for this.
I typically use Python for data analysis, especially the incredibly useful pandas and matplotlib libraries.</p>

<p>Outside of this, I love reading, tinkering with and building assorted trinkets/toys and weight lifting.
I plan on using this blog to post on a range of subjects which I have found both interesting and useful over the years.
As such, content may vary greatly.
In particular, I&rsquo;m trying to read a large number of new books with the broadly ambitious aim to read at least one on average every week.
This ambitious tends to often be thwarted by running out of new books to read.
I typically read a lot of print books, not because I am a luddite as I have previously bought, and read, a lot of kindle books.
But mainly because of the concept of ownership and what happens to such books if Amazon or some other company were to change its terms of service.</p>

<p>I am a bit of an information junkie, which I&rsquo;m trying to control as it does tend to consume a lot of my time.
Short form information, which tends to skirt a subject and not really cover it in depth is not exactly a great source of information.
As such, I&rsquo;m attempting to read more literature, long form articles and in depth coverage of topics.
In addition, contributing to these by writing about them is something I want to initiate and this is a good first step.</p>

<p>Finally, I have no set schedule for updating this blog although I will attempt to do so as frequently as my interest permits.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up Octopress with Ubuntu]]></title>
    <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/2013/05/08/setting-up-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-08T19:41:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/2013/05/08/setting-up-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Right, so this post will serve as a general overview as to a couple of the difficulties I had when setting up Octopress and Ruby.
I mainly use Python for my day to day analysis work and as such have little experience with Ruby.
I used rbenv for my installation and a couple issues arose which were a bit of a pain to sort out as googling appeared to let me down here.</p>

<p>So a couple things. If you are using Ubuntu then you need to use .profile instead of .bash_profile.
If done right the bottom two lines of the following should be.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>cat ~/.profile
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>export PATH="$HOME/.rbenv/bin:$PATH
</span><span class='line'>eval "$(rbenv init -)"</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p></p>

<p>Another issue which may arise is the difference between the system, and rbenv ruby installation.
The commands you are looking for here are as follows.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>rbenv versions # Will list the installed versions of rbenv
</span><span class='line'>rbenv local &lt;build&gt; # Will set a local version of ruby for the specific folder
</span><span class='line'>rbenv global &lt;build&gt; # Specify the global build of ruby to use.
</span><span class='line'>ruby --version # List the current version of ruby</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>I recommend playing around with each of these commands until you&rsquo;re comfortable switching between different versions of ruby.
In my initial installations I was having a lot of difficulty with different versions of ruby in different locations.
Generally, just a major annoyance to say the least.</p>

<p>Once these two issues were sorted out installation was pretty simple overall.
Hopefully if anyone else is having similar difficulties this post may point them in the right direction.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll update this post if needed or if I remember something new.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
