<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: web development | Electric Python]]></title>
  <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/categories/web-development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-03T20:51:08+13:00</updated>
  <id>http://NigelCleland.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nigel Cleland]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Experimenting with Flask and Web Development]]></title>
    <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/2013/06/01/experimenting-with-flask-and-web-development/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-01T18:09:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/2013/06/01/experimenting-with-flask-and-web-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m currently experimenting with using Flask for a bit of Web Development.
I&rsquo;ve never done web dev before and it has been an interesting learning experience so far. I&rsquo;m going to create a fairly simple tracking app for the gym etc, basically get a Database set up and some logging going on.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Once this is done, I&rsquo;ll try and extend it and get some fancier features going on, visualisations etc. It will be interesting working with these to see how python can be used in such a fashion. May end up dictating some of the other work I do as well which I may want to expose via websites.</p>

<p>This post is currently a work in progress, where I&rsquo;m up to so far</p>

<h2>Flask</h2>

<p>Flask is a python micro framework which is used for web applications.
It&rsquo;s small, contains very few lines of code, and relies heavily upon two other libraries Werkzeug and Jinja. I&rsquo;m currently implementing the project using a module type approach as follows</p>

<p>```
trackme/</p>

<pre><code>runserver.py
trackme/
    static/
        style.css
    templates/
        # templates
    __init__.py
    database.py
    views.py
    models.py
    forms.py
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Currently:</p>

<ul>
<li>models contains the SQLAlchemy tables</li>
<li>database contains the SQLAlchemy setup infor</li>
<li>views contains the flask page views</li>
<li>forms contains the WTForms Forms</li>
<li><strong>init</strong>.py contains the app itself</li>
</ul>


<h2>SQLAlchemy</h2>

<p>SQLAlchemy is a library which is used to create a bit of magic when it comes to SQL databases. Currently I&rsquo;m just running a local SQLite database and I&rsquo;m not too too worried about anything surrounding this as this is just a personal fun project at the moment.</p>

<h2>WTForms</h2>

<p>WTForms, this is designed to make Forms far far easier to use. I&rsquo;m still getting my head around a lot of this but I&rsquo;ve made good progress so far.</p>

<h2>Templates: Jinja 2</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m currently not really sure how to create my own templates, nor what these are really doing but it&rsquo;s something I plan on learning more about as I go.</p>

<h2>CSS</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t really know a hell of a lot about CSS but I guess I&rsquo;m going to have to find out!</p>

<h2>Plotting</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m currently not to sure what I&rsquo;m going to use for plotting things out, I&rsquo;m currently leaning towards either d3.js or vincent. I&rsquo;ve been looking for an excuse to try something apart from matplotlib for awhile now so will just have to see how this goes.</p>

<h2>To do:</h2>

<p>Wow, the list of things to actually get done to make this up and running are intense. I guess I can separate these into broad functionality steps.</p>

<ol>
<li>Ability to add workouts quickly and easily
1a. Begin writing tests to ensure that everything works</li>
<li>Ability to view workouts easily</li>
<li>Add support for profiles</li>
<li>Figure out templates, more html and templates to beautify the app a touch.</li>
<li>Implement graphical plots for progress</li>
<li>Add measurements, e.g. weight/size etc to help track progress</li>
<li>Begin extending the app to track other aspects (e.g. food/stretching/w.e.)</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
