<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rbenv | Electric Python]]></title>
  <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/categories/rbenv/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-20T19:33:39+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://NigelCleland.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nigel Cleland]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up Octopress with Ubuntu]]></title>
    <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/2013/05/08/setting-up-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-08T19:41:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/2013/05/08/setting-up-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Right, so this post will serve as a general overview as to a couple of the difficulties I had when setting up Octopress and Ruby.
I mainly use Python for my day to day analysis work and as such have little experience with Ruby.
I used rbenv for my installation and a couple issues arose which were a bit of a pain to sort out as googling appeared to let me down here.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So a couple things. If you are using Ubuntu then you need to use .profile instead of .bash_profile.
If done right the bottom two lines of the following should be.</p>

<p>```
cat ~/.profile</p>

<p>export PATH=&ldquo;$HOME/.rbenv/bin:$PATH
eval &rdquo;$(rbenv init &ndash;)&ldquo;
```</p>

<p>Another issue which may arise is the difference between the system, and rbenv ruby installation.
The commands you are looking for here are as follows.</p>

<p><code>
rbenv versions # Will list the installed versions of rbenv
rbenv local &lt;build&gt; # Will set a local version of ruby for the specific folder
rbenv global &lt;build&gt; # Specify the global build of ruby to use.
ruby --version # List the current version of ruby
</code></p>

<p>I recommend playing around with each of these commands until you&rsquo;re comfortable switching between different versions of ruby.
In my initial installations I was having a lot of difficulty with different versions of ruby in different locations.
Generally, just a major annoyance to say the least.</p>

<p>Once these two issues were sorted out installation was pretty simple overall.
Hopefully if anyone else is having similar difficulties this post may point them in the right direction.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll update this post if needed or if I remember something new.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
