<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Uncited work | My Escape]]></title>
  <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/categories/uncited-work/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-18T09:00:25+13:00</updated>
  <id>http://NigelCleland.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nigel Cleland]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Perfection is the enemy of itself]]></title>
    <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/2013/09/30/perfection-is-the-enemy-of-itself/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T21:51:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/2013/09/30/perfection-is-the-enemy-of-itself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A bold title for a personal essay but a thought which has been kicking around the back of my mind for a while now.
Perfection, as a goal often leads to poorly executed, unfinished, bloated projects.
The very nature of seeking the perfect solution often dooms the searcher to no solution, a less than worthwhile result.
This post will expand my thoughts in this area, as well as illustrating some opposing methodologies which should hopefully serve the reader well.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>To expand upon my premise I must take a short divergence into some personal anecdotes.
The first anecdote is that I go through transitional periods of both extreme productivity and extreme procrastination.
If I can find a project, or a problem which fascinates me then I can literally lose myself in the moment, and find the oft mentioned sense of flow commonly experienced by deeply skilled practitioners.
This post is now about those moments, those are moments to be husbanded, guarded jealously and ruthlessly exploited when they arrive.</p>

<p>Instead, this essay is about those other moments, those moments which you find yourself on a four hour youtube binge, or reading poorly worded terribly thought out comments on reddit.
This is a post about those periods in my life when I cannot get started, when I lose myself in a mental haze of self destructive melancholy.
I don&rsquo;t like these phases, I consider my time valuable and numerous other individuals have confirmed this to me both monetarily and through the expenditure of their own limited time.</p>

<p>As such, how can I limit my own self destruction?
How can I use my time in such a way as to be in a continuous state of advancement?
The phrase, live each day as if it were your last is disgraceful in its implications.
If a day were truly my last then I would be out buying hookers, blowing through my entire savings and having one of the most amazing parties of my life.
Instead, a better philosophy would be to live each day so that the following day will be better.
Under such a philosophy exercise, education, the pursuit of new skills, forming new relationships are all valuable worthwhile endeavours.
It is from this state of mind that I&rsquo;ll be approaching the rest of this topic.</p>

<p>How does this relate to my thesis topic, that perfection is the enemy of itself?
I implore the reader to think back to their own learning and assess whether the lessons I&rsquo;ve gleaned are of any value to them.
We often hear statements regarding mastery of a particular subject requiring 10,000 hours, in fact we hear this so much it has begun to lose meaning.
I pose the situation of a person who learns the same one hour lesson 10,000 times as compared to the 10,000 different one hour lessons, that is the extreme scenarios.</p>

<p>The person who has studied the one hour lesson a plurality of times will have excellent knowledge of that particular lesson.
However, who is to say that the 10,000th time provided a greater mastery over the particular skill than the 9,999th lesson?
How about as compared to the 5,000th lesson?
The 2,000th?
If we were to plot such a relationship we would discover a clear scenario of diminishing returns, yet this still does not give us any information regarding how many lessons are optimal.
Such an example is absurd but it does serve to illustrate the point that continuous repetition of the same material has negligible value.</p>

<p>We consider the second extreme, of the individual who has learnt 10,000 different lessons.
Here, there exists a number of competing scenarios.
Scenario one, the relationship between mastery and repitition initially follows a steep upward trajectory.
In such a situation each additional lesson provides reduced marginal value as compared to the preceding lesson and therefore the individual gains maximal marginal utility from each possible lesson.</p>

<p>The second possibility is that marginal utility follows a class S-curve pattern.
That is, the initial lesson provides a small amount of utility, and that subsequent lessons will increase marginal utility, to a point, before a taper begins.
This curve is recognisable in many instances of social sciences, for example the product adopters curve (e.g. early adopters to mass market to the last remaining hold outs).
If the lesson utility follows such a curve then the individual who studies many lessons briefly will gain reduced utility.</p>

<p>Both of these scenarios have considered the assumption in that learning one particular skill is independent of any other skills.
However, such a vacuum dependent theory fails to translate appropriately to the real world.
Consider two possible effects, translated knowledge and crowding out.</p>

<p>Translated knowledge occurs when knowledge in one particular domain positively influences knowledge in a second, unrelated domain.
For example, if you read more speculative literature then I will in turn speculative that you have a greater grasp of ambiguities than a corresponding version of you which does not read said literature.
That is, knowledge and learning in one discipline has effected a second domain.
Knowledge in which this general rule applies is incredibly empowering, taken to an extreme this could imply that to get better at things all that is required is a general improvement.
Clearly, at the absurd level this idea falls flat, however I do consider it of some merit and will return to it shortly.</p>

<p>The second scenario, crowding out occurs due to limitations in human short term recall and our ability to process information.
Although the human brains ability to process information is vast, it is not perfect.
Humans can only consider a limited number of scenarios into the future, we often use short term heuristics for decision making and none of us are perfectly rational entities.
Given such prior limitations I consider the case of a human whose brain is continuously saturated with information.
Would we expect such a person to have a high level grasp, of well, anything? Or would we expect such a person to simply be a walking talking collection of randomly assorted facts with no logical capacity to smoothly integrate them into a wider body of knowledge and understanding?
I expect that given too much information the human brain would reject such an overload of information as to be useless.</p>

<p>Thus, given our two scenarios both of which are over 10,000 hours I come to the following general conclusions.
The first is that human knowledge in a particular domain most likely follows a S-curve.
There exists some point, given a purely static field, in which our marginal appreciation will transition through an inflection point, switching from accelerating returns to decelerating returns.
However, this statement is lessened in intensity if a field is continuously changing, although such a field, if the rate of flux is too great, will prevent all mastery from occurring.</p>

<p>The second conclusion reached is that as we increase our knowledge in one particular domain we will expect some of the generalities to provide benefits in other domains.
Although no substitute for specific knowledge in a particular field, this general skill transferral will assist the individual in either accelerating the aforementioned S curve, or providing a solid foundation.
This is broadly the basis of many forms of schooling.
For example as we learn how to form more complete sentences, this partially translates to our ability to write better paragraphs.
However, the ability to write a perfect sentence does not imply the ability to write a perfect paragraph, nor a novel.
The general skill is transferred, not the specific.</p>

<p>The third conclusion reached is that an individual who spreads themself too thin, amongst too many fields, will never truly master any of those fields.
That is, there is a hierarchy of domain mastery which can be expected.
For example, a person could expect to master a single domain, or they could reach a high level of competency in two to four domains.
An individual may be competent in a dozen different domains, but we would not expect the average individual to be a true master in any of those specifically.
Likewise, a person who has spread himself amongst hundreds of fields will only have a cursory knowledge of these fields.
I note that within an individuals knowledge a distribution will exists, that is they will have localised mastery of particular domains.
However, this localised mastery is relative to their mastery of the remaining disciplines.
As compared to a disciplined external party their competence will pale in comparison.</p>

<p>Now, after the not so short sojourn we may return to the thesis at hand, Perfection is the enemy of itself.
Isn&rsquo;t such a statement a form of cognitive dissonance on my part?</p>

<p>Here I qualify this statement through a narrowness of application.
Perfection is the enemy of itself when it is single mindedly applied to a single, specific, task not a general outcome.
For example, consider a software project.
A considerable amount of time may be spent on the project attempting to make a perfect, elegant, even beautiful piece of code.
Something which works, is a pleasure to read and makes you feel like it was a worthwhile sense of accomplish.
In fact, many hours could be spent crafting this particular item, the line by line debugging and optimisation.
The continuous re factoring is ultimately wasted time and resources.</p>

<p>I instead propose a better outcome.
Consider what happens in three months times, when you find that said piece of code no longer fits the use case.
I would guarantee that the same individual in their second attempt would be able to produce an even better piece of work.
Likewise, if three months later on they had to (for whatever reason) do it again.
Now, here I am almost leading down the wrong pathway in that I appear to be suggesting that continuously repeating yourself is a good idea.
It&rsquo;s not.</p>

<p>What is a good idea though is continuously learning from the lessons learnt in the first case and applying those to the subsequent cases.
Broadly, you get better by doing, by continuously expanding your knowledge in a general field through specific applications.
If you are a wood worker seeking to incorporate more curved cuts in your work you do not practice the same cut over and over.
Instead, you seek to cut as many curves as possible, of all shapes and sizes and you learn how your tools work in such situations.
Of course you will need to repeat specific cuts, because there is no substitute for mastery of a single task than repetition of said task.
However, always keep in mind the diminishing returns present, and be aware of the distinctions between adequate, good, great and perfect.
Striving for perfect is not something you plan for, but good and great are worthwhile outcomes.</p>

<p>So far, I have illustrated some of the issues of both too much, and too little, attention upon particular tasks.
Yet, this speaks nothing as to the goldilocks zone, of just right.
Simply, this particular point will vary form task to task, individual to individual but some broad guidelines may be considered.
We may also extend these into a few real world strategies.</p>

<p>We must begin to recognise which knowledge is related within our cognitive sphere of influence.
Look for the similarities between disciplines, don&rsquo;t operate in a vacuum and don&rsquo;t brainlessly repeat tasks repetitively.
It is a special form of insanity to repeat the same task over and over again and expect a different result.
If you are getting different results, you many want to look into functional programming.</p>

<p>Recognise that if you want to get better at a particular skill that it will take a consistent application of time, energy and cognitive resources.
But do not focus these three inputs upon too narrow a field.
I thoroughly enjoy rock climbing, but it is naive to think I will ever progress in the sport if I stick to climbing the same wall, in the same way, over and over again.
However, if I were to practice upon a number of different walls my general skill would improve, if I were to fixate upon a particular wall within the greater subset I would likely be better at that individual one.
Such an analogy is broadly applicable to other situations in life.</p>

<p>Thus, I feel comfortable at this point taking an attempt at addressing my topic.
Perfection is the enemy of itself because a single narrow minded pursuit of a particular, specific, goal limits all second order effects.
By such a narrow field of vision you ignore all possible transferral of knowledge between domains.
Diminishing marginal returns quickly sets in as the mind is stagnant and not exposed to new ideas.
The authors general skill set atrophies as their brain rewires itself for a single task.
Quite simply, seeking perfection on a specific project is like practising the same lesson ten thousand times.
As such, perfection is the enemy of itself, because the individual has self limited themselves.
In effect, by such a single minded focus they have capped the denominator and are seeking to raise the numerator.
By broadening their basis the individual can simultaneously raise both sides of the equation resulting in a better, but still not perfect project.
The single minded pursuit has resulted in a worse outcome than the somewhat lackadaisical general improvement with a slight concentration on the project.</p>

<p>Upon answering the topic I will now seek to expand upon some possible strategies as a result of this.
These strategies are intended primarily for myself.
As I mentioned in the introduction to this essay, I&rsquo;m a terrible procrastinator in certain situations and it is something which I am desperately seeking to fix.
The broad strategies I wish to consider include cognitive displacement, inwards search and active procrastination.
These are names which I have completely made up on the spot and as there is nothing new under the sun I&rsquo;ve likely plagiarised these off someone.
Oh well, I don&rsquo;t care.</p>

<p>Cognitive displacement is a simple principle in that the human body has a limited capacity for in depth learning and knowledge.
That is, the mind may become overwhelmed and will not retain information passed to it.
This is often observed in individuals, who suffering from cognitive overload, stress, anxiety, or a number of other factors experience a degraded mental acuity.
I do not imply that there is a 1:1 replacement between new knowledge and old knowledge, rather that new knowledge is essentially shed before taking root.</p>

<p>Every individual has a different tolerance for new mental experiences.
This tolerance is influenced by factors such as intelligence, education, fatigue, alcohol, stress and noise.
It remains to the individual to thus limit their own cognitive input to ensure maximum retention.
This necessitates the removal of particular sources of information, for example low quality television, radio, print and other mediums.
In the modern world this is doubly difficult.</p>

<p>We live our lives saturated in low value content, and we do not possess the appropriate mechanisms to filtering this content.
In particular, we must devote cognitive resources to assessing the importances of any informations, and what actions are required from this.
Furthermore, if no action is required, and the information is not needed in the past then such activity is an unnecessary expenditure.
On the internet, such forms of low value, non actionable information are prevalent.
Memes, news from foreign countries, domestic scaremongering, celebrity gossip, pseudo scientific articles and other poorly written tripe are all a factor.
Much of this information is designed to draw in the reader, through imagery, sensationalist titling and other parlour tricks.</p>

<p>We thus live in a world where the very act of being aware of our surroundings exhausts our mental faculties.
The danger is that we create individuals with short attention spans, a wide, but shallow knowledge of disparate events and views founded more on sensation than reason.</p>

<p>Moving on from such a dull topic we reach inwards search.
In opposition to cognitive displacement, inwards search is a positive, actionable step which an individual may take to sharpen their focus.
Here, I seek to avoid labels, such as meditation or other labels which people use to dismiss an activity they do not agree with.
Instead, I will call it either inwards search or active focussing.</p>

<p>Enough of definitions and book keeping.
Inwards search is the act of looking within yourself in order to achieve a desired outcome.
There are many ways which people can achieve this and I will speak in generalities here.
To begin, almost by definition, the act requires solitude, and the absence of external simulation in the sensory realm.
I finding a location in which you can control the visual realm e.g. blind folds, dark rooms.
Ideally the place should be quiet and comfortable and be removed from other individuals intrusions.</p>

<p>Once you have found such a location, simply make yourself comfortable and sit or kneel.
The goal is to find a position in which you can remain for at least twenty minutes.
Upon reaching this position, seek to clear your mind of each of the distractions currently weighing upon you.
Empty your mind of the stresses, the worries the mental intrusions.
Instead, focus upon a particular situation, a problem, or simply drift.
Here, be rigid with your thoughts, you don&rsquo;t care about the dishes, laundry or all of the other miscellaneous details you need to cover to live.
During this period of time you must simply be.</p>

<p>Now, how is this different from meditation or other quackery sounding buzzwords.
The simple answer is that it is not.
The long answer is that this time is whatever you want it to be.
All that I am recommending is that you make the time.
Find some peace, quiet and solitude, and simply unwind and be yourself for the day.
You may hate this, you may love this, but either way I highly recommend that you try it at least a few times.
Do note, that initially you will find it very difficult to still your mind to the distractions.
You have most likely ingrained the habit of always being aware deep into your subconscious.
This will take time to rectify.
I personally like to take this time to stretch as well, I know that it&rsquo;s meant to be a period of absolute stillness but I find the deep stretch to be personally helpful.</p>

<p>The next topic of consideration is active procrastinations.
We all procrastinate to differing degrees and we do it in a number of different ways.
Here, we must take a two pronged look at the issue.
The first prong tackles the why of procrastination, it is thoroughly worthwhile to justify to yourself why you are undertaking a particular issue.
You&rsquo;ll likely find yourself unable to answer.
However, the caveat here is that you&rsquo;re most likely going to be in the mood where you just don&rsquo;t care that much.
Thus, it becomes very hard to break outside of the vicious feed back loop which arises.
You procrastinate because you&rsquo;re stressed and worn down.
Because you procrastinated you feel even more stressed, you push yourself harder, become more anxious and get even more worn down.
This causes you to procrastinate more.
Rinse, repeat ad infinitum.</p>

<p>Another name for this is burnout.</p>

<p>How can we tackle this issue?
I want the answer to this question just as much as you do.
I have a very serious battle with procrastination, the feedback loop I was describing above is what I&rsquo;m currently experiencing.</p>

<p>The strategy I&rsquo;m going to try is to take more breaks, earlier.
Broadly, target my productive periods into shortened super intensity periods where I attempt to reach a state of flow.
In the in between stages I want to reach a state of active procrastination, which I will define later.
Intense focus is not required for hour upon hour.
Instead, it is necessary to fully form the mental puzzle of a problem in peace and quiet.
Solve said puzzle, and then let it go from your mind.
Once you have tackled this issue relax and reach into some less cognitively intensive tasks.</p>

<p>What I am currently stuck in is the awful middle ground.
I am never truly at rest.
Yet, I am never truly at my best.
Instead, I meander through a middle ground of low efficiency and poor cognitive awareness.
This stops me from relaxing, exhausts me and wears me down considerably.
This, is my attempt at changing this behavioural pattern.</p>

<p>The second prong is to look at the how we are procrastinating.
What activities are currently being used as a procrastination aid in this respects.
For me, my weakness is rapid content websites such as news sites, reddit, hacker news et cetera.
These sites are like kryptonite to me.
I love being continuously exposed to information, new ideas and new topics.
It stimulates me, and that therein is the problem.</p>

<p>I need to wean myself off my information crack.
To initially accomplish this I&rsquo;m deleting my tablet apps which have this purpose.
Setting up custom hosts files on my computer and installing a website blocker.
I&rsquo;m going to be using the Chrome extension StayFocusd for this.
Ideally the goal is that I just get off the internet in general.
It is good for some things, but it isn&rsquo;t healthy to live your whole life through it.</p>

<p>This is my personal procrastination method.
It has limited value to me personally so I need to replace it.
Here, we introduce the concept of Active Procrastination.
This idea goes hand in hand with the earlier concepts introduced of having a super intensity period followed with lulls.
Here, Active Procrastination serves to fill those lulls.</p>

<p>The following is a list of activities which I consider to be worthy of consideration for the lulls and Active Procrastination.
Your own definitions will obviously differ, so be an adult and write your own list.</p>

<ul>
<li>Weight Training</li>
<li>Cooking something new (Not repeating an easy recipe)</li>
<li>Reading</li>
<li>Writing non seriously</li>
<li>Stretching, Yoga, Meditation, Mindfulness</li>
<li>Music Instruments</li>
<li>Walking</li>
<li>Socialising</li>
<li>Urban Exploring</li>
<li>Hiking/Tramping</li>
<li>Photography</li>
<li>Drawing/Painting/Caligraphy</li>
<li>Programming</li>
<li>Mechanical Maintenance (e.g. Car/Motorbike/Bicycle etc)</li>
</ul>


<p>In addition the following is a list of activities which fit a grey area.
I include them because they definition is not hard and fast and they do improve life in some shape or form.
However, some people do use this as procrastination aids.</p>

<ul>
<li>Cleaning</li>
<li>Rote Cooking (E.g. something simple and easy to make)</li>
<li>Busy work</li>
<li>Shopping (When not taken to excess, everyone needs new clothes)</li>
</ul>


<p>The remainder should be cut from the life where possible.</p>

<ul>
<li>Mindless internet browsing</li>
<li>Rapidly paced content driven websites (e.g. aggregators, news websites, youtube, twitter, facebook)</li>
<li>Excessive masturbation (Key word being excessive)</li>
<li>Pornography usage (Nothing against it personally, it is included as many people, guys especially, use it as a time filler, this may fit a grey area for some people.)</li>
<li>Debating people on the internet. Just don&rsquo;t.</li>
<li>Television</li>
<li>Gossip Magazines</li>
<li>Most forums</li>
</ul>


<p>The reader should begin to notice a clear trend occurring in the three different types.
The goal of active procrastination is replace unhealthy habits with healthier ones.
This time then becomes self improvement time, makes you a more interesting person and should hopefully make you happier.
All of the content on the cut list is essentially modern day soma, cutting you off from the world you live in and replacing it with a fake world of manufactured bliss.
I will write more about these concepts at a later date however.</p>

<p>This I&rsquo;m afraid brings this very long post to a close.
I have rambled off the initial topic somewhat.
That is to be expected when it&rsquo;s late at night and you&rsquo;re reaching close to the 4k word mark however.
I will expand in more depths upon some of the points in this essay at a later date.
I may also revise this essay somewhat as I take the time to proof read it in the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
