<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Essay | My Escape]]></title>
  <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/categories/essay/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-16T21:57:16+13:00</updated>
  <id>http://NigelCleland.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nigel Cleland]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The concepts of doing nothing at all]]></title>
    <link href="http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/2013/10/11/the-concepts-of-doing-nothing-at-all/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-11T13:37:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://NigelCleland.github.io/blog/2013/10/11/the-concepts-of-doing-nothing-at-all</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What is the act of doing nothing?
When we are doing nothing, are we truly doing nothing?
Is this a problem?</p>

<p>Three very simple questions yet quite possibly without a simple answer.
I intend to explore each of these short questions at times individually, at times together in the hope of coming to an answer.
The art of doing nothing, and it is an art, is something which has been lost to many within society as it requires a somewhat maligned train of thought to reach it.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>First, we must explore that the act of doing nothing is.
I ask you to picture the last moment in time in which you had no mental cares, no physical need to do anything.
You were safe, warm, most likely by yourself with full freedom to accomplish anything you set yourself to.
Picture this moment, but discard any times when your mind was on other issues, social engagements or things which caused you stress.
Discard any moment when you were worried about bills, worried about sex, about social drama, about the worried.</p>

<p>Include only those times when you were truly relaxed and, although I hesitate to use the phrase, at peace.
If you are like me, and I would assume most of society this period of time is as much myth as reality.
Yet, it seems so simple.
This is what I mean when I speak of nothing.
In my mind, this act is so important as it presents an opportunity to disengage from the world around us.
To metaphorically recharge ourselves and to place ourselves in a situation where we may be relaxed.</p>

<p>This concern with the act of nothing may appear strange but I assure you I have very good reasons.
Most particularly, I have great difficulties with being overwhelmed by what I need to do and what is expected of me.
I typically do not have many issues performing once I set myself to the task, but the initial beginning phase is the hardest to me, and I often become anxious about this.
Hence, I am seeking to place my thoughts about nothingness into terrible prose, so that I may hopefully reach that state myself.</p>

<p>Why is this important?
All of those occasions when you cannot relax, when the stress and worries of the day are with you take something from you.
The rob you of your mental alertness, your ability to process new information and introduce negative thoughts into your life.
None of these outcomes are desirable, if they are desirable to you I suggest you visit some serious professionals.</p>

<p>So I propose a challenge to both myself and the zero other people who read this.
Practice, at least once per day the art of switching off and doing absolutely nothing.
Practice emptying your mind and letting go of the bullshit.
It&rsquo;s not important.
Really, it isn&rsquo;t, and it&rsquo;s stopping you from tackling the things which are important.
So practice, just a few minutes, or longer, but at least once.
Build it into a system, a habit, don&rsquo;t make it a goal.
Simply make it something you do and see if the results are as you expect.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m certainly going to try, because I&rsquo;m tired of being tired and overwhelmed.
It&rsquo;s just no fun.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
